<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reformado, precisely charactered by a transformed church-warden, at a vestry, London. The motion of the world this day is mov'd the quite contrary way.</title>
            <author>Transformed church-warden.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92330</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E95_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11062</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858928</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858928</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155799</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92330)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155799)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 17:E95[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reformado, precisely charactered by a transformed church-warden, at a vestry, London. The motion of the world this day is mov'd the quite contrary way.</title>
                  <author>Transformed church-warden.</author>
                  <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A satire upon the Protestant party." -- Thomason Coll.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to George Wither in the Wrenn catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: imprint cut away and last blank page wanting.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  Great Britain --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155799:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REFORMADO, Preciſely Charactered by a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church-warden, at a <hi>Veſtry,</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The <hi>Motion</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> this day</l>
               <l>Is mov'd the quite contrary way.
<figure>
                     <q>HODIE SIC VERTITVR ORBIS.</q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>— Mutant quadrata rotundis.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <figDesc>a celestial globe rests on a lobster's back in the foreground of a mountainous coastline with a fortified harbour and sailing ship in the sea</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </l>
               <l>Doe thou, theſe froward <hi>Motions LORD,</hi> reſtraine;</l>
               <l>And ſet the <hi>World</hi> in her due courſe againe.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:155799:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155799:2"/>
            <head>THE REFORMADO, Preciſely Charactred by a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Church-warden, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a bleſſed <hi>Eaſter (Brethren)</hi> that raiſed mee up againe to this ponderous <hi>ſervice;</hi> and if any <hi>Feaſt</hi> be worthy of annuall <hi>ſolemnity,</hi> my <hi>Vote</hi> is, that the <hi>Feaſt,</hi> of <hi>Easter</hi> (though moveable, ſhall ſtand faſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <hi>Antiquity</hi> tells me, that the <hi>Office Gardiani Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ccleſiae,</hi> is an <hi>Office</hi> inſtituted and dignified by the <hi>Fundamentall, knowne, Common, and Statute Lawes of this Kingdome,</hi> (as for the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and Canon Lawes,</hi> I have held them <hi>execrable,</hi> ever ſince the <hi>High Commiſsion</hi> departed with a <hi>Duck</hi> in the mouth on't) and this honour is not to be conferr'd upon any, but ſuch as are judicious and <hi>fidele,</hi> and able to imploy (couragiouſly and <hi>ſincerely</hi>) the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtock of Treaſure, and diſcretion belonging to the pariſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not, I conceive, yet out of your memory how <hi>accurately</hi> I heretofore ſteer'd the affaires of <hi>Parochiall Government;</hi> nor out of mine, with what <hi>alacrity</hi> you ſubmitted to it: My <hi>deportment</hi> (then correſpondent to thoſe times) was a faire Character of <hi>ſquare</hi> dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and was, I preſume, a prime motive to your <hi>thundering accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations,</hi> (which the eccho of this roofe witneſſed to the next Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh) in <hi>re-electing</hi> me the <hi>principall Reformado</hi> of this <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Polity.</hi> In the exact <hi>execution</hi> whereof, I intend (with the aſſiſtance of my younger <hi>Brother,</hi> (whom I ſhall well educate for
<pb facs="tcp:155799:3"/> the next yeare) to uſe ſuch preciſe diligence (for the remainder of my time) as may <hi>caſhiere</hi> many <hi>feares</hi> and <hi>jealouſies,</hi> and ſettle many things, (hitherto <hi>incompos'd</hi>) in ſuch a gracefull <hi>poſture,</hi> that the <hi>trust</hi> of you, that <hi>confide</hi> in me, ſhall not in the leaſt <hi>ſcruple</hi> be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd. But you muſt remember the old word <hi>Diſtingue tempora,</hi> and then (regarding the <hi>turning round</hi> of the <hi>times</hi>) you will conceive that the <hi>wind</hi> ſits in another corner; and I muſt <hi>move</hi> by other <hi>Rules</hi> than formerly: for I am now more ſpiritually illuminated and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with ſounder <hi>principles.</hi> The <hi>Civill Law</hi> is partly <hi>plunder'd,</hi> the <hi>Canons (old and new)</hi> have <hi>recoyl'd on the Canoniers,</hi> the nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Army of Articles</hi> is <hi>routed,</hi> the <hi>Oath ex Officio</hi> put out of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and the <hi>bottomleſſe &amp;c. Oath</hi> is <hi>ſwallowed up.</hi> The <hi>Caſe</hi> thus ſtanding, and that you may have a <hi>right understanding</hi> of your <hi>Moderator,</hi> take an <hi>Epitome</hi> of my <hi>Reſolution;</hi> but withall take this foure-fold <hi>advertiſment</hi> along with you.</p>
            <p n="1">Firſt, that I will follow the preſent <hi>Faſhion</hi> ſo far in my <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> as to keep no <hi>Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">Secondly, that my <hi>interſperſion</hi> of <hi>Latine</hi> ſhall no way authorize the uſe of that <hi>Beſtiall Language in the Pulpit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">Thirdly, that if my <hi>phraſe tranſcend</hi> your <hi>plumbeous Capacity,</hi> you ſhall eſteem it the fruit of my <hi>liberall education,</hi> before I ever <hi>handled the Sheeres, or fingr'd the thimble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">Fourthly, That you, who (for ſolid <hi>edification</hi>) fall ſo nimbly to your <hi>Brachigraphy,</hi> ſhall not let this <hi>Oration</hi> paſſe <hi>Grub-ſtreet</hi> without my <hi>approbation,</hi> nor (if it may be) untill a <hi>ſweet Panegyrick of my ſister</hi> Hannah's <hi>compoſing may be annexed unto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the <hi>Weather-cock,</hi> which is an eminent, <hi>gilded, hollow, craking, comb'd,</hi> and <hi>variable creature,</hi> and doth ſo wonderfully <hi>ſympathize</hi> with me in all, and with the preſent <hi>turning times</hi> in ſome ſpeciall reſpects, that I doe <hi>Order</hi> it to continue <hi>Statu quo prius;</hi> and the foure <hi>Fanes</hi> adorned with the <hi>initiall letters</hi> of my unſpotted <hi>Name,</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſedulous attendants</hi> upon't in my Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to goe which way ſoever it goes. From the <hi>Weather-cock</hi> I ſhould have <hi>fallen</hi> immediately upon the <hi>Leads,</hi> but an <hi>Iron Croſſe</hi> hinders
<pb facs="tcp:155799:3"/> me in my way, which (with all other <hi>Croſſes moveable</hi>) ſhall be aboliſht, that nothing may goe <hi>croſſe</hi> in our <hi>Deſigne.</hi> The <hi>Leads</hi> I find <hi>prophan'd</hi> with the <hi>Images</hi> of corrupt <hi>hands, irregular feet,</hi> and with <hi>unſanctified names;</hi> they ſhall therefore bee removed, <hi>puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with fire,</hi> and <hi>converted</hi> into <hi>Bullets</hi> to button the <hi>boſomes</hi> of the <hi>common adverſarie,</hi> and to <hi>ſeale</hi> up the <hi>brazen</hi> fore-heads of the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Cavaliers.</hi> This being <hi>diſpatcht,</hi> I have made a fair <hi>through-fare</hi> to the five <hi>Bells,</hi> which had, indeed beene <hi>out of frame</hi> long ſince, were it not that, ſometimes they <hi>ring the Changes, (ſweetly conſenting</hi> therein with mee) and ſometimes <hi>audaciouſly proclaime</hi> an <hi>unknowne Victory</hi> to the <hi>over-credulous,</hi> which inflames all their <hi>zeale</hi> and <hi>Faggots</hi> in an inſtant. There is an impeachment as ſtrong as a three-fold <hi>cord,</hi> againſt foure of the Bells.</p>
            <p n="1">Firſt, they were <hi>baptized</hi> before the yeares of <hi>diſcretion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">Secondly, three times a day they <hi>pollute</hi> the <hi>tune</hi> of <hi>the</hi> fourth <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">Thirdly, they have <hi>Idolatrous Inſcriptions</hi> upon them, as (with a little of the <hi>Sextons</hi> help) I have curiouſly diſcovered. For, upon the firſt <hi>Bell</hi> there is <hi>peccatoris;</hi> on the ſecond <hi>mei;</hi> on the third, <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere, &amp; Domine</hi> upon the fourth.</p>
            <p>Now, judge you (<hi>Brethren</hi> (who would ſeeme, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, to bee as wiſe as your <hi>Officer in chiefe</hi>) is not <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine miſerere mei peccatoris, notorious</hi> and <hi>groſſe Idolatrie?</hi> are thoſe words fit to bee utter'd by a <hi>Profeſſor,</hi> unleſſe it be with a <hi>holy detestation</hi> of ſuch <hi>puddle?</hi> Ah, I ſee by the <hi>devout ſhaking</hi> of your heads, that your <hi>Braines</hi> are troubled about it, that your <hi>hearts abhorre,</hi> and ake to thinke upon ſuch rotten <hi>traſh.</hi> Well, it is high time, that theſe foure be no longer hanged, but <hi>Drawne,</hi> and <hi>Quartered,</hi> that they with the abhominable <hi>Braſſe</hi> upon the <hi>Monuments</hi> of our <hi>Idolatrous</hi> Anceſtors, (I paſſe not though an old Aunt of mine lyes mouldering under one of them) may <hi>Concurre</hi> for the making of <hi>Ordinance</hi> to batter down the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their <hi>Donors.</hi> The <hi>Wheeles</hi> (being but <hi>Hemicircular</hi>) ſhall <hi>Hang</hi> there like <hi>Meteors</hi> betweene <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:155799:4"/> but the <hi>Ropes</hi> may ſerve (the next Seſſions) at the wooden <hi>Tripode</hi> two miles out of <hi>Town,</hi> for the uſe of thoſe that wil not <hi>ſtretch</hi> their <hi>endeavours</hi> for <hi>Independency</hi> the Liberties of the <hi>Dawes,</hi> (our <hi>beloved Allies</hi>) will, by this meanes, be inlarged; and wee will further <hi>confirme their Incorporation,</hi> that from time to time they may make ſuch <hi>Ordinances,</hi> as are <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with the <hi>Priviledges</hi> of their <hi>houſe,</hi> and <hi>conducible</hi> to the <hi>bene eſſe</hi> of their <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> keeping their Courts <hi>ad libitum,</hi> in the <hi>upper Region</hi> of the <hi>Tower,</hi> as we doe here in the <hi>Veſtry.</hi> The <hi>Clock</hi> and <hi>Diall,</hi> becauſe they goe <hi>round,</hi> ſhall take their uſuall courſe, onely by a pious fraud, they ſhall go ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>earlier</hi> in the <hi>morning</hi> and <hi>later</hi> at <hi>night,</hi> than <hi>Truth would</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of. This ſhall be my godly <hi>Revenge</hi> upon three <hi>crook-legg'd youthes</hi> of mine, who had rather encounter (at home, with whole <hi>Brigades</hi> of <hi>Egyptian</hi> foot <hi>ſouldiers,</hi> than <hi>advance a yards length</hi> (in a <hi>Holy cauſe</hi>) againſt a <hi>ſingle Cavalier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have dwelt ſomewhat long in the <hi>Steeple:</hi> now wee will come to <hi>Church,</hi> where (in the firſt <hi>place</hi>) I ſee the Font taking up ſo much <hi>roome</hi> that would be <hi>capable of two double Taffata Gownes;</hi> which I confeſſe, I ſhould not ſo ſtrictly have obſerved, had not the <hi>diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented yoak-fellows</hi> of my <hi>Dyer,</hi> &amp; <hi>hot-Preſſer,</hi> (who are <hi>crowded up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the doore) drawne me to it.</hi> Away with it, this <hi>Font is abhomin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> a <hi>Baſon</hi> will be more apt for the <hi>ſervice,</hi> ſince it is not our <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe</hi> to enjoy ſuch a <hi>bleſſed River as our deare brethren and ſiſters at Hackney</hi> are waſht withall. And thoſe lofty <hi>Pewes</hi> which are higher by the <hi>head</hi> and <hi>ſhoulders,</hi> than their <hi>Inferiours,</hi> ſhal be <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed,</hi> that our <hi>grave Matrons,</hi> and <hi>ſweet heavenly minded ſiſters,</hi> (whoſe <hi>poſture,</hi> turning their faces <hi>weſtward,</hi> is moſt <hi>amiable</hi>) may have a more cheerfull <hi>influence</hi> upon us their <hi>Governours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Pulpit,</hi> (in reſpect of the <hi>forme</hi> of it, (being almoſt <hi>round</hi>) is <hi>tolerable,</hi> although my neighbour <hi>Zacharie</hi> the <hi>Cooper, Caprecious veſſell</hi>) could <hi>faſhion</hi> out one more ſeemly, and to better purpoſe; but the <hi>ſituation</hi> of it (looking too much towards <hi>revolted Yorke</hi>) ſhall ſuffer a <hi>Reformation,</hi> and at the <hi>Pariſh charge,</hi> it ſhall be ſecured with a ſubſtantiall <hi>Padlock,</hi> leſt they, whom the meer naturall man calls <hi>profound, pious, loyall,</hi> and <hi>Orthodox Divines</hi> ſhould ſaucily <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude</hi> it. I can partly tell you the <hi>poore condition</hi> of thoſe <hi>ſilly Prieſts;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:155799:4"/> Aſſoone as they aſcend the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> they fall on their <hi>knees</hi> for <hi>divine Aſsiſtance,</hi> as if they could not be <hi>cock-ſure</hi> of it at all times: then they have a <hi>premeditated prayer,</hi> not much exceeding a quarter of an <hi>houre,</hi> wherein they <hi>petition</hi> for <hi>peace and unity,</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> for <hi>Kings, Queenes, Princes,</hi> and ſuch kind of <hi>people,</hi> and ſupplicate our Saviour Chriſt for <hi>choyce bleſsings</hi> upon <hi>Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops,</hi> whom we have found (by the <hi>Spirit</hi> that we lead <hi>about us</hi>) to be the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Limbs</hi> of <hi>Antichrist.</hi> After this <hi>meſſe</hi> comes the <hi>Sermon,</hi> which is the greateſt part of a <hi>weeks ſtudy, (written</hi> perhaps, over and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) yet, may be delivered in an houre. Their <hi>Concluſions,</hi> (which we are neither able, nor willing to underſtand, are confirmed by <hi>Scripture, Fathers, and Reaſon.</hi> They conſult with the <hi>Originall Tongues,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Authors</hi> as are called <hi>Authentick</hi> and <hi>Claſsicall,</hi> fetching their water from the <hi>Primitive ſprings,</hi> becauſe they (emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Casks) thinke they cannot have as <hi>pure</hi> neerer home: So, by their great skill in <hi>Divinity,</hi> gracefully attended (forſooth) with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of <hi>humane learning,</hi> they will exhort us to ſtudy <hi>to be quiet,</hi> to <hi>trie the ſpirits,</hi> to be <hi>Charitable, moderate, obedient to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and to doe things according to <hi>Order,</hi> with a great deale of ſuch hungry <hi>thin ſtuffe;</hi> I have utterly done with them and theirs, and am heartily overjoy'd, that ever I thought of this happy <hi>Pad-lock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Pulpit-Cloth</hi> was the <hi>Legacy</hi> of a blind <hi>Zelot,</hi> as appeares by that <hi>Jeſuiticall badge, (I. H. S.)</hi> upon't; for, as ſome of our learned <hi>Profeſſors</hi> doe conceive, <hi>I.</hi> ſignifies <hi>Idolatry. H. Hereſie, S. Superſtition.</hi> Oh, here's good <hi>worke!</hi> What but flat Popery can be expected from a <hi>Pulpit</hi> aparreled with ſuch a <hi>Livery?</hi> Theſe <hi>Letters of gold</hi> ſhall be delivered to the <hi>Finer</hi> to make <hi>Silver</hi> withal, and the <hi>Velvet</hi> (becauſe it deſerves a better <hi>Wardrobe</hi> and the coſtly infirmities of the <hi>Testator</hi> ſhould be <hi>hidden</hi> by our <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi>) ſhall be <hi>converted</hi> into <hi>Window-Cuſhions</hi> for my <hi>new-reformed Parlor,</hi> where I intend frequently to entertaine thoſe <hi>immaculate Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,</hi> which the un-regenerate call <hi>Conventicles.</hi> The <hi>Houre-glaſſe</hi> ſhall be <hi>turned</hi> out of doores; for our <hi>extemporall Teachers</hi> may not keepe <hi>time</hi> with <hi>Clocke</hi> or <hi>Glaſſe;</hi> and ſo, when they are out, (which is not very ſeldome) they can take leiſure to come in againe; whereas, they that <hi>meaſure</hi> with <hi>meditations</hi> by the <hi>houre,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:155799:5"/> are often <hi>gravell'd</hi> by complying with the <hi>Sand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Organs</hi> are of <hi>Leviticall,</hi> or <hi>Popiſh inſtitution,</hi> and like the <hi>breath</hi> of a <hi>Baſilisk,</hi> they deter hence the two <hi>prime Grandees of the Pariſh,</hi> (the <hi>moſt Celeſtiall Almanack-Makers,</hi> and beſt <hi>tempered Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> that ever lived by <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>earth.</hi>) They drowne the <hi>Virgin-melody</hi> of the <hi>Gallerie,</hi> and <hi>middle Alley;</hi> and againſt our wills bring our <hi>confuſed Notes into Order;</hi> therefore, though I adventure my <hi>neck</hi> (as that <hi>deſperado</hi> did in <hi>Worceſters Cathedrall,</hi> and his <hi>Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor</hi> at <hi>Cheap-ſide</hi> Croſſe) I will ſet them ſuch a <hi>Flat</hi> that ſhall lay them <hi>breathleſſe on the pavement.</hi> This <hi>Romiſh merchandize</hi> will yield good <hi>Engliſh Coyne</hi> at <hi>Pauls</hi> or the next <hi>Cathedrall</hi> that is not <hi>Bankerupt.</hi> The <hi>Table</hi> of <hi>Degrees</hi> prohibited in <hi>Marriage</hi> is obſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lete, and ſo is marriage it ſelfe as here it hath beene uſed; for I ſee no ground to the contrary: but when all things <hi>are common</hi> (as they <hi>ought</hi> to be) a man may <hi>marry, whom, when, where,</hi> and as <hi>often</hi> as hee will. This is a very ſhort, but a ſweet and comfortable <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> to you (my <hi>deare</hi> and <hi>attentive Auditory</hi>) and ſo the ſuddaine <hi>pricking</hi> up of the <hi>eares</hi> doth aſſure me.</p>
            <p>Let us now, take a little ſurvey of our <hi>Church-books.</hi> The <hi>Bible</hi> (which alwayes comes firſt to my ſight and handling) hath a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <hi>Apochryphall Obſtruction</hi> in the very <hi>Bowells</hi> of it, which is of a <hi>Malignant influence</hi> upon the whole <hi>Body.</hi> This is compoſed of ſuch Hiſtories, as bind not our <hi>credence,</hi> and <hi>morality</hi> which ſhall not be the rule of our <hi>Practiſe;</hi> it muſt needs be preſently <hi>expur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi> Yea, the <hi>Canon</hi> it ſelfe, in reſpect of <hi>Tranſlation</hi> is not free from <hi>infirmity</hi> (and indeed it is no marvaile, ſince ſo many <hi>mitred heads</hi> had their <hi>hands</hi> in the doing of it.) The <hi>Geneva verſion</hi> is farre beyond it: But old <hi>Hugh Broughton,</hi> if hee might have been ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, had exceeded them both; A learned <hi>Synod,</hi> (without either root or branch of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi>) muſt be the onely <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> to <hi>cure</hi> this <hi>evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Errata</hi> of the <hi>Book of Common prayer</hi> (as ſome call it) or rather the <hi>Lithurgy</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> were they expreſt at large, would <hi>over-bulke</hi> the <hi>Bible;</hi> yet the ravenous <hi>Eſau's</hi> of the world, had rather loſe all their <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Proprieties</hi> (which are their <hi>Birth-right</hi>) then one <hi>meſſe</hi> of this <hi>red</hi> and <hi>black Pottage;</hi> I
<pb facs="tcp:155799:5"/> will not <hi>contaminate</hi> my <hi>lippes,</hi> nor abuſe your <hi>chaſte eares</hi> with ſo much as naming any errors that are in it; but referre you to <hi>Rabbi Lewis Hughes</hi> (the glory of the laſt <hi>Brittiſh Druides</hi>) and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others, who have, already, <hi>ſmitten</hi> this <hi>Belphegor</hi> under the <hi>fift rib.</hi> It further behoves us that the <hi>ſinging Pſalmes</hi> be reſcued from the back of ſuch a <hi>Monſter,</hi> and from thoſe other <hi>humane inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Te Deum, Da pacem Domine, &amp; Quicunque vult:</hi> but, <hi>whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will</hi> that any (except the 150 <hi>Pſalmes</hi>) be <hi>continued,</hi> may doe well, (in my <hi>underſtanding</hi>) to defend <hi>Robert Wiſedome's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is an errour in <hi>John Jewells</hi> workes, but it is an error with a <hi>witneſſe,</hi> and, although it be <hi>palliated</hi> over <hi>Jure Divine,</hi> yet it is <hi>inſtar omnium errorum,</hi> and hath in it the <hi>ſpawne</hi> of all Abominations; it is beyond pity, that ſuch a <hi>Gemme</hi> ſhould ever be <hi>defiled</hi> with ſo baſe a <hi>Cogniſance; He was a Biſhop.</hi> The very word <hi>Biſhop,</hi> (I feare I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in naming it ſo often) imparts all the <hi>miſchiefes</hi> that are <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive</hi> to a <hi>Common Church</hi> or <hi>State.</hi> Your <hi>holy indignation (breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren) is well expreſſed</hi> by the preſent <hi>groanings</hi> of your <hi>ſpirits,</hi> but be comforted, for theſe <hi>ſtall-fed Lordly Prelates</hi> muſt come ſhortly, to their <hi>fatall Banquet. Eraſmus</hi> his <hi>Paraphraſe</hi> hath found the more favour hitherto at my hands, becauſe he ſometime wrote a <hi>Tract</hi> in the prayſe of <hi>fooliſhneſſe;</hi> but when I remember ſome <hi>popiſh paſſages</hi> in his <hi>Colloquies,</hi> which I <hi>read</hi> when I was at <hi>Merchant Taylers ſchoole;</hi> I cannot well <hi>reſent</hi> his beſt <hi>labours.</hi> The <hi>book</hi> of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us &amp; Rex</hi> is <hi>a pamphlet</hi> quite out of my <hi>books</hi> meerly, for the <hi>Oathes</hi> ſake that is in it. Theſe Oathes <hi>of Supremacy and Allegiance</hi> are <hi>bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding things;</hi> the <hi>latter</hi> was impoſed upon me when I was a <hi>novice,</hi> and it hath ſo hampered me this year, that I would fain, if poſſible, caſt off theſe <hi>manacles:</hi> for it is almoſt <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelfe to us that ſhould be <hi>independent,</hi> to be ſo pinion'd.</p>
            <p>The Book of thirty nine <hi>Articles</hi> is in many things <hi>diametral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> oppoſite to our <hi>fundamentall Principles,</hi> it muſt neceſſarily bee with-drawn, or farewell our <hi>Diana</hi> for ever. All the afore-named <hi>corrupt volumes</hi> ſhall bee tranſlated out of <hi>the Church,</hi> and all the <hi>Iſles</hi> thereof, into <hi>little Brittaine,</hi> or elſe into <hi>Smith-field.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:155799:6"/>
            <p>Wee have but one <hi>Manuſcript, (I meane the Register)</hi> and that muſt be <hi>Corrected;</hi> for the names of all thoſe that were <hi>crost</hi> at their <hi>Baptiſme, ring'd</hi> at their <hi>Marriage,</hi> or <hi>pray'd</hi> over at their <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall</hi> ſhall be <hi>cancell'd.</hi> No <hi>Names</hi> henceforth ſhall bee ingroſſed here, unleſſe they were firſt <hi>Registred</hi> in holy <hi>Writ:</hi> nor will wee keep a <hi>Record</hi> of the <hi>names</hi> of ſtrange <hi>Preachers</hi> any more; for, they may <hi>deliver good Doctrine in the City,</hi> who never had <hi>Orders</hi> or <hi>good name</hi> in the <hi>Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Communion-Table</hi> hath, long ſince, regain'd its <hi>ancient Name,</hi> and <hi>Site;</hi> and I hope our <hi>nimble-joynted Maſſe Priests</hi> ſhall never be ſuffered to <hi>offer</hi> or <hi>cringe</hi> there, any more: But I will be bold, with the <hi>round pillars</hi> that inviron'd it, (when the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous Superſtition</hi> is ſcrap'd off) to make an impregnable fence for my hoſpitable <hi>Buttery.</hi> I doe well remember the <hi>Plate,</hi> (hee that can forget <hi>Plate</hi> this yeare, may be <hi>Ordered</hi> to forget it for ever.) I know to what <hi>furnace</hi> it might be <hi>convey'd,</hi> to what <hi>Vſe</hi> and <hi>Forme</hi> converted, and by what meanes <hi>multiplyed</hi> and <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſecur'd;</hi> but there is ſuch a <hi>Noli me tangere</hi> upon it, that I dare not finger the twentieth part of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pariſh Caſh</hi> yet, is ready to my hand, and I will preſume to ſeize upon a <hi>fleece</hi> of it, to maintaine at the <hi>Church-doore,</hi> a <hi>guard of Long-tayl'd Vociferadoes,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Giles Cripple-gate,</hi> and <hi>Olaves old Jewry</hi> had, leſt the <hi>Conjuring Letany</hi> ſhould <hi>ruſh</hi> in upon the <hi>fourth</hi> and <hi>ſixth</hi> day of the week, (<hi>Heatheniſhly</hi> called <hi>Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> and <hi>Friday</hi>) that <hi>Prayers</hi> be not read <hi>againſt Pride, vaine-glory, and hypocriſie, &amp;c.</hi> and, leſt the <hi>Babylonian garment,</hi> (the <hi>Surplice</hi>) be <hi>ſhouldered</hi> in, againe among us; for, to Profeſſors of our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion,</hi> no <hi>ſmock</hi> is more <hi>odious,</hi> than that of the <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor any <hi>Petitions</hi> more terrible, than thoſe that would <hi>obliterate</hi> our <hi>principall Character.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of our Dim-eyed <hi>Anceſtors</hi> could ſee unhappily, to make their <hi>Simplicity Legible</hi> upon the <hi>Church-Walls,</hi> by ſetting up the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> (as they tearmed it) which is too narrow a <hi>directory,</hi> or <hi>Summary</hi> of our <hi>Petitions:</hi> The <hi>Ten Commandements,</hi> which are not (I conceive) abſolutely <hi>Obligatory</hi> now, under the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:155799:6"/> the <hi>Creed,</hi> which is not (I believe) <hi>Apostolicall;</hi> nor am I bound to <hi>ſtand to't.</hi> Theſe ſhall, in <hi>good manners,</hi> give the <hi>Wall</hi> to choy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and I will be the <hi>Master of the ſentences,</hi> to ſelect them. The taking downe of the <hi>popiſh pictures,</hi> out of the <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes,</hi> and bringing them, (by a legall tryall) to a ſecond <hi>Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> was a laudable, and <hi>tranſparent worke</hi> of my <hi>immediate Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor;</hi> But, <hi>nil ſimul inventum &amp; perfectum, Rome was not built in a day, nor can it be demoliſht in a yeare,</hi> (unleſſe this <hi>great year,</hi> or the next does it. There is one pretty ſcandalous <hi>Baby</hi> yet left in the <hi>Eaſt-window;</hi> it hath a <hi>trim Coat</hi> on, and an <hi>Orient luſtre</hi> a-about the <hi>head</hi> on't.) The <hi>Sextons Grandam,</hi> (blinde <hi>ſoule</hi>) who well remembers the ſetting up of it) ſhew'd it me, and told me it was our <hi>Bleſſed Lady;</hi> but truely, if ſhe were my <hi>Mother,</hi> and as <hi>high as heaven,</hi> I will (as <hi>Duty</hi> bindes me) make her <hi>Kiſſe</hi> her <hi>mother earth</hi> once againe. And the <hi>Angels</hi> on the roofe of the Church, (though they did coſt five ſhillings a piece the <hi>gilding</hi>) ſhall have their <hi>Wings</hi> clipt, and fall downe to <hi>ſalute her.</hi> The day whereon this <hi>pious worke</hi> ſhall be done, may be called the <hi>Deſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Lady;</hi> and (if Authority will permit) it ſhall be <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendered</hi> next unto my <hi>Birth-Day,</hi> which they call <hi>ô Sapientia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queene <hi>ELIZABETHS Monument</hi> was put up (at my charge) when the <hi>Regall Government</hi> had fairer credit among us than now: and her <hi>Epitaph</hi> was one of my Brother <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than's</hi> beſt <hi>Poems,</hi> before hee abjured the <hi>Univerſity,</hi> or had a thought of <hi>New-England.</hi> I have had no ſmall ſtrugling within me about the <hi>toleration</hi> or <hi>abolition</hi> of this <hi>Statue;</hi> and at laſt, have reſolv'd it ſhall continue, but with a <hi>Curtaine</hi> to vaile it, that wee may regard, or diſ-regard it at our pleaſure: For, methinks in Forty foure yeares reigne, ſhe might (if ſhe pleaſed) have <hi>bated the Beaſt of Rome</hi> to better purpoſe, and wrought a more <hi>through Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> yet, (notwithſtanding Her <hi>Majeſties omiſsions</hi> of ſorrowfull memory) of her ſucceſſor (King <hi>James</hi>) had not been too <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>learned,</hi> aſſwell as too <hi>peaceable,</hi> for our <hi>Generation,</hi> and his <hi>Divines</hi> too <hi>ſinewy</hi> for ours to <hi>grapple</hi> with at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> we had finiſht that <hi>worke</hi> long agoe; which never ſince, till now could
<pb facs="tcp:155799:7"/> meet with ſo faire an opportunitie. The <hi>Eſcutcheons</hi> that are <hi>quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered</hi> over our heads in the body of the Church, are <hi>Emblemes</hi> of thoſe <hi>honours</hi> which ſome of our noble <hi>Progenitors</hi> purchaſed with the hazzard of their <hi>bloud,</hi> in <hi>defence of Religion, known Laws,</hi> and <hi>liberty of the ſubject.</hi> I will give them leave to be <hi>hang'd.</hi> But when I take notice of the <hi>Royall Arms,</hi> and their <hi>Motto (Beati pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifici.</hi>) I cannot for the preſent, but enteraine ſome <hi>mutinous, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall, rebellious</hi> thoughts; and a <hi>furious zeale</hi> would ſoon drive them into <hi>action,</hi> were it not that <hi>Conſcience, allegiance,</hi> and <hi>Honi Soit,</hi> upon the <hi>blew garter,</hi> did <hi>countermand</hi> it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some alteration would be of poſtures, and names as well as things;</hi> For truely, I cannot, with an <hi>upright Conſcience, condeſcend</hi> to kneeling at the <hi>Sacrament:</hi> we are not not required to be ſo flex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ible in a <hi>ſuperstitious adoration;</hi> my advice is, that we either ſit familiarly, or ſtand to't couragiouſly; nor ought our <hi>Gesture</hi> to bee the ſame now, at the <hi>Goſpell, Creed,</hi> or <hi>Glory be to the Father, &amp;c.</hi> as it was <hi>in the beginning.</hi> Theſe and other like <hi>Geſticulations,</hi> came firſt into this Countrey, from the <hi>City</hi> which <hi>ſtands on ſeven hills,</hi> and thither (with all ſuch <hi>Baggage</hi>) let them <hi>trudge</hi> againe. As for <hi>names,</hi> I ſee no warrant, but under <hi>the man of ſinnes owne Seale,</hi> that this Church ſhould bee call'd Saint <hi>Clements;</hi> nor indeed, (as I have learned, ſince I was <hi>inlightned</hi>) that it ſhould be called a <hi>Church.</hi> Wee, onely, can diſcerne who are <hi>Saints,</hi> who <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates;</hi> and it is not hard to finde, who and what this <hi>Clement</hi> was, and yet deale gently with him.</p>
            <p>But I ſee an approaching <hi>Reformation</hi> in this very particular; the <hi>Pariſh Clerks</hi> have already <hi>paſſed</hi> it by their <hi>weekly Bills,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>under-Officers</hi> (as zealous as he that laſh't a <hi>Car-man</hi> for whiſtling the tune of a Pſalme to his horſe) doe puniſh our <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Harlots</hi> for crying Saint <hi>Thomas Onions,</hi> (although they know ſuch <hi>Aegyptian Roots</hi> cannot be <hi>ſanctified.</hi>) The Law is the ſame concerning Saint <hi>Johns Wort,</hi> and <hi>Carduus Benedictus.</hi> And for this building, which hitherto wee <hi>ignorantly</hi> called <hi>a Church</hi> it is indeed but an old pile of Stones, (I hope to ſee more ſumptuous, and magnificent Priſons ere long) It was built at
<pb facs="tcp:155799:7"/> their charge who vainly, thought a decent <hi>Barne</hi> or <hi>Stable</hi> too homely for a <hi>Chriſtian Synagogue,</hi> and was <hi>conſecrated</hi> (ſaving your preſence) by ſome <hi>Prelate,</hi> as Superſtitious as the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> The verity of it is, <hi>We</hi> are the <hi>Church,</hi> and this <hi>Fabricke</hi> (till we are otherwiſe provided) is but a <hi>meeting place,</hi> (where to our great griefe) there is too often, a <hi>miſerable mixture</hi> of the <hi>prophane</hi> with the <hi>godly;</hi> for redreſſe whereof, there is no other way then (in a tumultuous faſhion) to preſent ſuch a <hi>Petition</hi> as <hi>Authority muſt</hi> not contradict.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ingens opus,</hi> and <hi>Maſter-piece</hi> of all, now calls <hi>aloud</hi> for your quickned <hi>attention,</hi> inflamed <hi>zeale;</hi> and well-ſetled <hi>endevours;</hi> I meane the <hi>diſcreet-election</hi> of an <hi>able,</hi> and <hi>ſincere Paſtor,</hi> whoſe <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell</hi> I have conceived briefely thus.</p>
            <p>Hee muſt not <hi>proceed</hi> from <hi>Wales,</hi> or either of the <hi>Vniverſities;</hi> for then we ſhall never underſtand him; nor yet from <hi>Jericho,</hi> leſt the <hi>gravity of his beard</hi> give us cauſe to ſuſpect the truth of his <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſmes,</hi> and <hi>inſpirations;</hi> but he ſhall be a <hi>a ſmooth, ſweet yong man, wel deſcended</hi> (not from <hi>Levi,</hi> but) from the <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Gad,</hi> or <hi>Man-aſſes,</hi> and trained up in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> the Iſle of <hi>Silly,</hi> or (if you pleaſe) in our owne <hi>neighbour hood,</hi> where wee have good choyce of ſuch whoſe <hi>Mechanick profeſsions</hi> have left them to make the Pulpit (as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe the ſword) their <hi>quum nemini.</hi> Here are <hi>Felt-makers</hi> that can <hi>roundly</hi> deal with the <hi>block-heads,</hi> and <hi>neutrall Demi-caſters</hi> of of the <hi>world: Coblers</hi> who can give good <hi>Rules</hi> for <hi>upright-walking,</hi> and <hi>handle Scripture</hi> to a <hi>Bristle: Coach-men,</hi> who know how to laſh the <hi>beaſtly enormities,</hi> and <hi>curb the head-ſtrong inſolencies of this brutiſh age, ſtoutly exhorting us to ſtand up for the truth,</hi> leſt the <hi>wheel of destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction roundly over-run us.</hi> We have <hi>Weavers,</hi> that can <hi>ſweetly</hi> informe <hi>us of the Shittle-ſwiftneſſe of the time,</hi> and <hi>practically tread</hi> out the <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſsitude</hi> of all <hi>ſublunary things,</hi> till the <hi>web</hi> of our life be cut off. And here are <hi>Merchants</hi> of my <hi>Profeſsion,</hi> who can <hi>ſeparate the pieces</hi> of <hi>Salvation</hi> from thoſe of <hi>Damnation, meaſure</hi> out every mans <hi>Portion,</hi> and <hi>cut it</hi> out by a <hi>thread,</hi> ſubſtantially preſſing their <hi>poynts</hi> till they have <hi>faſhionably finiſht up their worke,</hi> with a <hi>well-bottom'd concluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:155799:8"/>
            <p>Out of this <hi>Croſſe heap</hi> (wherewith wee are ſo comfortably ſurrounded) we may <hi>pick</hi> ſuch a one, that with a <hi>Stentorian voyce,</hi> (making more uſe of his <hi>Lungs,</hi> and <hi>noſe</hi> then <hi>nature</hi> requires) ſhall reprove our <hi>ſinnes</hi> in that <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>meaſure</hi> as we would have him, ſhall couragiouſly ſound an <hi>Alarme</hi> to <hi>Battaile,</hi> and tell us the <hi>event of a war before it beginnes,</hi> by <hi>expounding old Viſions</hi> and <hi>Propheſies,</hi> better than hee that was in <hi>Pathmos.</hi> Hee ſhall not need to travaile for <hi>Orders</hi> to the <hi>Prelaticall Hierarchie,</hi> hee ſhall receive <hi>Orders</hi> from us: I have drawne up ſome of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready for him; and by theſe you may judge of the <hi>whole; ex ungue leonem,</hi> as we us'd to ſay.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Habit</hi> ſhall be a <hi>high crown'd Hat, a black leather Cap,</hi> a ſad <hi>medley Cloake,</hi> and <hi>Jerkin</hi> of the ſame, <hi>Violet Hoſe,</hi> and <hi>Ruſſet Stockings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Laudreſſe</hi> ſhall evidence his hatred of <hi>white Linnen;</hi> and his <hi>Barber</hi> ſhall ſo <hi>roundly indent</hi> with his <hi>Head,</hi> that our <hi>eyes</hi> may as well <hi>ſee</hi> his <hi>eares,</hi> as our <hi>eares</hi> heare his <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his <hi>fathomleſſe prayers</hi> he ſhall diſpenſe much with the third <hi>Commandement, and take the Lords name in vaine ex tempore;</hi> cutting out more <hi>worke</hi> for <hi>God</hi> in an houre and a halfe, than a <hi>ſober man</hi> can expect ever to be performed by him that is <hi>moſt wiſe;</hi> and if at any time (forgetting himſelfe) he pray for the <hi>Kings Majeſty,</hi> it ſhall be with <hi>ſuch diſtractions,</hi> and <hi>Dilemmaes,</hi> that we can hardly diſtinquiſh it from <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Text</hi> muſt never be divided (we ſhall make ſufficient <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions</hi> among our ſelves) but he ſhall <hi>wander from</hi> it, as if it were not a <hi>tangible body,</hi> onely in <hi>caſe of pure neceſsity,</hi> he may (for a <hi>Moment</hi>) make it a place of <hi>retreat,</hi> and then <hi>friske</hi> abroad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Understanding</hi> ſhall bee free from all <hi>Liberall Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences:</hi> his converſation from all humanity, and his <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> from all <hi>figures,</hi> except <hi>Hysteron proteron, Hyperbole, Tautalogia,</hi> and other <hi>Flowers</hi> of the like ſent and colour.</p>
            <p>He ſhall uſe no <hi>Language</hi> but his <hi>Mother-Tongue,</hi> and the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:155799:8"/> (if he hath attained to it) making choyce of his <hi>Authors</hi> accordingly, ſuch as <hi>Aben Ezra, Rabbi David Kimchi,</hi> and the reſt.</p>
            <p>He muſt abominate the <hi>Greek Fathers, Chryſoſtome, Baſil,</hi> and all the bundle of ſuch unwholſome <hi>herbes;</hi> alſo the <hi>Latines,</hi> whom the <hi>Pope-bellied Gray-beards</hi> of the Towne call Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine, &amp;c.</hi> The intricate Schoole-men, as <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and our devilliſh learned Countrey-man, <hi>Alexander Halenſis</hi> ſhall not come within the ſpheare of his <hi>Torrid Braine,</hi> leſt his <hi>Pia Mater</hi> be confounded with their ſubtile <hi>diſtinctions;</hi> but (by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <hi>diſpenſation</hi>) he may (for <hi>names ſake</hi>) caſt an eye ſometimes upon <hi>Scotus:</hi> and; (when he hath marryed a ſiſter) upon <hi>Corna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius a Lapide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Engliſh Authors ſhould be curiouſly cull'd</hi> alſo: He muſt not ſo much as name <hi>Whitgift, Boyes, Hooker,</hi> nor any of the <hi>rabble</hi> of <hi>Anti-Brownists,</hi> or Conformiſts: But his chiefe <hi>guides</hi> ſhall be <hi>Knox, Browne, Barrow, Robinſon,</hi> and that never ſufficiently ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and admired <hi>Howes</hi> (not the <hi>Chronologer,</hi> but) one of our late and beſt <hi>Tranſlators</hi>) Hee was a man that feared not to come cloſe to the <hi>heeles of truth;</hi> but was a <hi>laborious</hi> applyer of ſtrong <hi>poynts</hi> to the <hi>last,</hi> and had alwayes a <hi>lift</hi> or two for the <hi>Back-ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</hi> If any one <hi>ſtood ſtobbornly</hi> on his <hi>Pantofles,</hi> he could <hi>worke</hi> him as pliable as <hi>Wax;</hi> if there were a <hi>Schiſme</hi> in his <hi>charge,</hi> both his <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Awle</hi> ſhould make up the <hi>breach</hi> in a <hi>zealous contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> He well obſerved the foot-ſteps of his <hi>Auditory,</hi> and graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted much <hi>goodneſſe</hi> into thoſe that had <hi>gone aſide, driving</hi> his <hi>Holy inſtigations ſo home,</hi> that, whereſoever they went, they were ſenſible of them. In a word, he was the <hi>hammer of all humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> a moſt induſtrious <hi>converter of ſoales;</hi> and in a ſhort ſpace, did ſet forth more <hi>works</hi> in <hi>Oxe-hides,</hi> than old <hi>Tostatus</hi> did all his life time. Oh— I can never mention his name, nor viſit his <hi>monument</hi> in <hi>Finzbury,</hi> but preſently theſe <hi>ſpirituall pangs</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize mee—Oh—<hi>He is gone, he is gone.</hi> But there is <hi>heavenly comfort</hi> provided for us, or our poſterity; for <hi>I</hi> was told, even now in any <hi>Viſion,</hi> that he ſhall <hi>come</hi> againe, and <hi>teach</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:155799:9"/> on earth before the <hi>last day.</hi> And now, heartily thanking you Holy Brethren for your preſent <hi>patience,</hi> I will proceed where I left.</p>
            <p>When our <hi>Soules</hi> are bleſt with a <hi>Doctor</hi> of theſe, and the like rare <hi>qualifications,</hi> the next conſiderable will bee his <hi>ſtipend</hi> (for this <hi>Oxe</hi> will not be <hi>muzzled</hi>) which I conceive (under favour) ſhould be the ampler, in regard there will bee little or no uſe of him for <hi>weddings, Churchings,</hi> and <hi>Burialls;</hi> which, in our late pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind times, yielded the <hi>Incumbent</hi> (as the Lawyers call'd him) a comfortable <hi>Revenue.</hi> I thinke well (with ſubmiſſion to your <hi>Judgements</hi>) that wee advance him to forty marks <hi>per annum</hi> but with this <hi>proviſo,</hi> that our <hi>benevolent Sisters</hi> ſhall not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited their voluntary contribution of <hi>money,</hi> (if the <hi>Plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> hath not ſent it marching into the field) or <hi>Plate,</hi> (if any be left upon the <hi>Cup-board) Linnens,</hi> and other neceſſaries, which I am confident will amount to twice as much. This was the meer <hi>motion</hi> of my <hi>Reverend Mother,</hi> and deare <hi>Siſter,</hi> whoſe voyce may be heard where mine cannot.</p>
            <p>And whereas we never continue long in any one <hi>Opinion,</hi> but <hi>ſeparate</hi> dayly, from <hi>Separation to Separation,</hi> I hold it expedient that once in every foureteene dayes, (which ſhall bee the new and full of the Moon, the true <hi>Moderatrix</hi> of our braynes) wee have a ſolemne meeting in my <hi>ſanstified parlour,</hi> where our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſhall give us a <hi>conciſe exhortation</hi> of two houres long, or ſome ſuch matter, and then we may <hi>admoniſh</hi> him of ſuch things as in the matter or manner of his former Labours, were not correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to our humours, and may direct him (for the future) how <hi>long,</hi> how <hi>broad,</hi> how <hi>high,</hi> and how <hi>deep</hi> he ſhall teach us; how <hi>gently</hi> or <hi>tartly</hi> he ſhall handle our <hi>ſores,</hi> and when hee ſhall <hi>reſtraine,</hi> when <hi>enlarge</hi> our Liberty. And then refreſhing our ſelves in a Chriſtian manner, with a chirping cup of <hi>Canarie,</hi> and ſuch good thing as the Gentlewomen will miniſter unto us (being devoutly <hi>conſecrated</hi> by a <hi>long-winded benediction</hi>) every one ſhall depart
<pb facs="tcp:155799:9"/> home with ſuch <hi>preciſe</hi> heedfulnes as may prvent the <hi>ſcurrilous tongues of the Malignants;</hi> for, (I muſt tell you) wee have a ſort of ſcoffing <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> that will undertake to ſee <hi>ſinne</hi> where <hi>God</hi> cannot; and with their <hi>black mouthes</hi> will perſecute the meekeſt <hi>Iſaac</hi> upon the earth.</p>
            <p>Theſe, with ſome other things (I know not well what) are the <hi>Compendium</hi> of my thoughts, leaving nothing <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall</hi> to the care of my Succeſſors, but the ſubverſion of the <hi>Croſſe-Ile,</hi> the <hi>demoliſhing</hi> of the <hi>Arches,</hi> (if without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger it bee <hi>feiſable</hi>) and the <hi>turning</hi> of the maine <hi>ſtructure North,</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> (which now moſt <hi>offenſively</hi> ſtands <hi>East</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi>) or taking it all aſunder for a purer <hi>Edification.</hi> Now onely remaines, that in a pretty <hi>Diminitive Vote,</hi> you pleaſe to give your Brotherly aſſent unto the <hi>premiſes.</hi>—</p>
            <p>Never was <hi>Vestrie</hi> ſhaken with ſuch a <hi>Thunder-clap!</hi> the Ayre ſeldome ſuffers ſuch a <hi>holy violence;</hi> your loud Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>clamour</hi> brought this earth into ſuch a fit of <hi>trembling,</hi> that (I am partly perſwaded) the <hi>Graves</hi> were in ſome doubt they ſhould be diſpoſſeſt of their <hi>Guests;</hi> But I am ſure this <hi>Gale</hi> hath driven out <hi>Billowes</hi> of joyfull <hi>Teares</hi> at my eyes, and <hi>blown</hi> my <hi>zeale</hi> into an <hi>extinguiſhable conflagration,</hi> which had wel-nigh <hi>puffed</hi> me up into another <hi>Extaſie.</hi> This is <hi>Vis unita</hi> indeed that can ſet all the Elements on worke thus at a clap. Your unanimous approbation, (my <hi>zealous breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren</hi>) obligeth my extreameſt <hi>abilities</hi> to the proſecution of my <hi>Intendments;</hi> reſolving as long as the old word <hi>(Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus indicat virum)</hi> ſtands firme, my <hi>demeanor</hi> ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe me to the <hi>life,</hi> and make me famous to <hi>poſterity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if the well-tuned <hi>Vox Populi</hi> of this Precinct will
<pb facs="tcp:155799:10"/> honour mee (the next <hi>Nativity-tide</hi>) to bee your proper <hi>Common-Counſell man,</hi> my learned <hi>Oratorie</hi> in <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> and <hi>Pious Devotion</hi> in the whole <hi>Service,</hi> ſhall render me as <hi>Pragmaticall,</hi> and <hi>Fanaticall</hi> a <hi>Member</hi> in the <hi>Civill-government,</hi> as poſſibly I can bee in the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>—Smel inſanivimus omnes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:155799:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
